Loretta Carter Hanes Collection 081
People's Archive, MLK Library
Loretta Carter Hanes Collection
1971-1990
People's Archive, MLK Library
Hanes, Loretta Carter
081
0.5 Linear feet
1 Boxes
Arrangement
Processed without series.
Biographical / Historical
Native Washingtonian Loretta Carter Hanes was an educator, historian, activist, and environmental public health advocate. She graduated from Miner's Teacher's College in 1949 and worked as a teacher in D.C. Public Schools for many years. While serving as a member of D.C. Citizens for Better Public Education, she met Margaret McNamara, who founded Reading is Fundamental (RIF). Hanes became a board member and, eventually, the Director of D.C. Reading is Fundamental. She was also a strong proponent of the celebration of D.C. Emancipation Day; in fact, thanks to her research and lobbying, Emancipation Day became an official holiday in the District in 2005. Additionally, Hanes played a significant role in the passing of legislation regarding the maintenance of water and sewer pipes in Washington, D.C. She passed away on August 21, 2016.
Custodial History
The materials in this collection have been with the Library since 1995. While there is no official record, it is assumed that Loretta Carter Hanes donated the collection.
Related Materials
Collection #002: District of Columbia Citizens for Better Public Education (DCCBPE) Collection
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of correspondence, notes, pamphlets, newspaper clippings, legal records, and legislative materials related to Loretta Carter Hanes' work with Reading Is Fundamental and the problem with sewage and water pipe breaks in Washington, D.C.
Legal documents; Correspondence; Legislation; Reading Is Fundamental, Inc.; Public utilities; Political activists; Women; African Americans; Black people
- Series 1
  - ANC- 4A, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bill number - 1-20 - DC Council, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bill number - 1-65 - DC Council, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bill to Authorize the Repair and Maintenance…, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Broken Pipes, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Citizens for Alexander, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 1974-1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Complaint for Damages, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence - T. F. Airis (with photographs), 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence - Antioch School of Law, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence - Drafts of Letters, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence - Friends of Neverson, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence - William J. Gardiner to Gilbert Hahn, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence - William C. McKinney, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence - Jerry A. Moore Jr., 1974 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence - NBC News, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence - B. J. O'Donnell, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence - Politicians, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence - George Reynolds to Gilbert Hahn Jr., 1971 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence - Judith Rogers, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence - Mayor Walter E. Washington, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence - Washington Gas, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Dr. Gridlock - Department of Motor Vehicles, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Financial Statements, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - First One Hundred Days Progress Report, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Forms, Undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - "Free Voice", April 13 1977 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Neighbors Inc., 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Northwest Boundary Civic Association Newsletter, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Notebook, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Notes, 1971-1990 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - "The Observer", April 23 1977 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Opening Statement, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Petition Regarding Heavy Equipment Travel on 4th Street NW, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Petition Regarding the Water and Sewer Repair Act, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Public Schools, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Reading Is Fundamental, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Service Area Committee, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Upper Northwest Coordinating Council - Special Forum, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Witness List - Public Hearing on Bills for Water and Sewer Pipe Maintenance, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 40)